alright class 4 is pretty simple it's
about the posture okay a viral channel
and meditation posture I think as a
teacher I mean once you've decided on
your own posture once you've got used to
your own posture you don't think about
it much but when you're a student it's
very important and and you want the
teacher to be clear about how you're
supposed to sit and things like that so
traditionally it's a big subject people
take it very seriously
okay so I think just be aware even if
you meditate every day and you you just
sit down and you do your regular posture
the people you're teaching the people
are gonna be teaching this course too
many of them have never meditated before
or they went to some not very
authoritative meditation somewhere and
they they want you to tell them how to
sit okay so it's good to think of it in
an organized way and in the ancient
books it's very organized the teaching
on how to sit is very clear and
organized okay so your presentation
should also be organized don't just say
okay do this you know like go through
each each of the eight parts one by one
because those also yoga is the same I
see a lot of yoga teachers people have
never done yoga before and then they
tell them bah bah you know when you're
teaching people who haven't done
meditation or yoga and they don't come
from that culture they don't come from
maybe they're in their country people
don't do that much you have to start at
the beginning okay
and so this is a very nice ancient
presentation of how to sit okay
posture all right mmm so there's eight
characteristics of the posture and now
go through them one by one
okay and what I'm encouraging you to do
is keep this list with you when you
teach meditation and go through the list
with people and help them okay
and same with yoga when you teach yoga
to new people what's the goal of a first
class in yoga that they come back that's
the only goal the rest doesn't matter
that you can do a headstand or you know
you know the Sanskrit words or it
doesn't matter at all to the new people
there's only one goal to a first yoga
class is that they come back and they
feel like they got some achievement that
they could do it you know so I I know my
first yoga teachers which are the
Jivamukti people David laughs Sharon
Gannon and Lady Ruth they in their
beginning classes they never do a post
that everybody can't do you see they
never do a post that's not everyone that
anyone in the class cannot do and and
they thought about it for a long time
and they that's how they design their
yoga class the same for meditation okay
it doesn't matter how much you know it
doesn't matter how many scriptures you
read it doesn't matter if you know the
Sanskrit or all that matters is that
they meditate okay and keep it in mind
when you teach meditation and it's hard
to get modern people to do something
every day it's extremely difficult to
change people people's habits I think
that's why the green stretch pen in
Mexico seeing is so it has such great
potential because you guys are teaching
kids and kids will do it you tell them
and adults don't so make it interesting
don't do anything they can't do okay and
your goal is only one thing that they
meditate for ten minutes every day and
if if you fail in that one thing then
you failed as a meditation teacher it
doesn't matter how long you can sit or
if you can do a headstand and cross legs
or something it doesn't matter it
doesn't help them okay okay so go
through the posture slowly make sure
they can do it okay all right so the
first posture is your legs what do you
do with your legs okay and traditionally
we sit in a full Lotus posture or half
Lotus posture in DCI we encourage people
to sit in a chair because we don't want
to make it difficult modern people don't
eat well they don't exercise much their
legs are a mess their knees are a mess
their back is a mess okay it takes years
to fix a modern person strut posture so
just be aware of that okay they're not
from ancient India they are people who
ate too much their whole life and sat in
a chair their whole life and breathe
pollution their whole life now they are
sixty-five percent of Americans are
obese that means almost double the
normal weight and they can't walk easily
their knees hurt so the worst thing you
can do is put them on the ground and say
do a full Lotus you know because they
can hardly their knees are already
damaged by overweight okay so be careful
with people's knees are very sensitive
extremely sensitive okay and so you also
I saw many people I had one student in
New York who damaged her knees for her
whole life and she used a cane some lama
insisted that she sit in a full notice
and she's used to came since she was
about 30
because I've done okay so don't push
people okay and the knees are very
sensitive they're the easiest thing in
your body one of the easiest joints to
hurt okay and then you think you're
being a great yogi and you're just
damaging your precious body okay so
don't be a hero
and don't let your students be a hero
you see somebody telling doing a full
Lotus to yell at them and after many
years you can do it okay but I think if
you're gonna be a good meditation
teacher you should watch your students
and you know who can do a full Lotus and
who cannot and don't let them hurt
themselves they are your responsibility
they're their knees are your
responsibility seriously okay and
they're I don't know there are many
great yoga teachers who had knee
operations and hip operations okay so
don't push it okay ask them to sit in a
chair all right now there's a big debate
you know should I put my left foot up
first and I put my right up for our
tradition is left foot up first okay all
right you know if you do a half Lotus
the left foot is up okay and if you do
the right foot
I don't care Buddha doesn't care okay
don't worry about it but in general left
foot up has some benefits okay according
to our tradition prana benefits and
you'll learn it about it when you reach
diamond weight teachings okay but
starting from the left is Varma Marga
its traditional for for our lineage okay
so usually we do things with the left
foot first okay so if you're gonna do a
half Lotus then put the left foot up
first okay I think something that my
yoga teachers never told me
until I met David Swensen who's a great
yoga teacher he came to my three-year
retreat and helped me and he didn't know
me
I just wrote him a letter and he came
and he's super famous and he took the
time to come and he said the most
comforting thing to me he I couldn't
talk but he could talk and he said
listen everybody has a different body
you know everybody has a different body
and there are some yoga poses
Geshe Michael that you will never do in
your life get used to it you know we all
have two or three poses at least that he
said look you can practice and practice
and practice and he's the only one who
did I think third series video in the
world in the world and he said look
there's just some things you can't do
everybody's body is different you know
and I like to say God gave you two yoga
poses it means there's two poses you can
do that nobody else can do I like to
look at the positive like I like this
one when people say I'm gonna take a
picture this I got a step or they asked
me to teach a class this is always in
there this one's always in the class the
ones I can't do our never in the class
okay so you know some people will never
be able to do a a folder safely okay
and don't don't you're not a bad person
okay your mom just didn't give you the
right bones you can write her a letter
tell her why why can't I do full Lotus
it's your fault
so anyway left foot up first if you do
do a full notice then
then the right foot okay and and that's
that's the tradition okay if you can
slowly gently with the help of your yoga
teacher learn to do a full notice and
comfortably then your meditation would
be better okay now in the DCI program I
say it will it won't be but in this
diamond mountain teaching I can tell the
truth your meditation will be better you
will progress faster if you can do okay
and I practice all the time when I eat
dinner
I always put one foot up you know me and
Tim had a fight today cuz there wasn't
enough room for all the chairs and I was
kicking him with my knee right and so I
try to do it all of it
everywhere even when I'm riding in the
car or that it met the movies I will put
my feet in a half Lotus and I'll just
get used to it okay so you can do that
and don't push it okay
yoga will help a lot okay that's the
first one when you teach it you have to
judge your student right that's a
teacher's first requirement you have to
look at your students and judge you know
how much should you tell them okay am i
lying when I tell DCI people to sit in
the chair and that there's no difference
if that's lying then there's no Abby
drama school
there's no sutra school there's no mind
only school
there's no lower middle school okay
understand you you have to adjust the
teaching to the students okay who did
that
yeah Buddha maybe it's okay
second characteristic the second of the
eight posterior so how do you put your
eyes your eye both okay and we talked
about it I guess yesterday
it's a very subtle thing and if you
meditate for
[Music]
amazing it's not bad okay as far as your
eyes people have a tendency to close
their eyes too hard okay so I think we
usually don't when you say muscle
usually think of this muscle but you
have muscles here and if you squeeze too
hard your you will get tired your
meditation will not go as well so try to
learn to close your eyes softly and
don't don't scrunch up this part of your
face okay there's a chakra here a small
chuckle called ajna chakra and don't
tighten it this this area especially
should be soft blue firmly between the
two eyebrows it should be soft okay try
to keep it so the minute you focus most
of us we squeeze it because you're
trying to focus then try to stay aware
of it and try to keep it soft okay and
that affects your eyes okay that affects
how you keep your eyes and again you
each person's body is different and your
prana is different from Maya prana so
the big thing you have to learn about
meditation is to experiment what's good
for you okay and maybe it's not what's
good for me so you know one pair of
jeans doesn't fit everybody we should
bring one pair of jeans and
and a tight one and make everyone put it
on so everyone has a different body and
you know don't say you have to fit into
one thing the important thing is to be
creative and experiment okay and try
many different ways of sitting there are
many many kinds of cushions okay
many many I have a friend dieter in New
Jersey one of my llamas clothes students
and he insisted on sitting on a wooden
block and I just looking at up my butt
hurt and he insists that this is the
best man you know and for him it was
good okay
the only thing the scripture says about
your cushion and again maybe it's not
doesn't apply to everybody but says the
back should be higher than the front
okay whatever you use the back should be
higher than the front but again people
have different buttocks their spinous is
different and the only mistake you can
make is to suffer for a long time with a
seat that doesn't work you know try many
different kinds of cushions you know and
for many years I watched what everyone's
doing I said can I try can I try your
cushion personally I like the recall
those things Hulse buckwheat hulls it's
a like a grain and you use the skin
right it's the skin of the grain and I
like it because it it changes according
to your bottom it will move around I
don't like the very tight tall ones okay
so I if it's me I would say buckwheat I
would also say chronically try to avoid
synthetic materials even in your
clothing when you meditate okay
it's oil it's carcinogenic okay
avoid a nylon or what is that stuff you
know all the polyester yeah try to use
cotton or wool try to use natural
materials in your meditation outfit okay
and in your meditation seat okay I have
a friend
Devorah she she uses three cushions she
puts two under her knees she puts one
under each knee and then she has a
bigger one for her bottom and it looks
pretty comfortable to me so if your
knees have trouble if you're not loose
here then do a lot of prenatal classes
that's what I did just kidding we got
those kids Tim speaking of prenatal
classes I gotta show off my new nieces
okay they are not my granddaughters
they're my nieces
[Music]
that's Nick and Aaron's new baby M&E
she's about three hours old or something
she still had goopy ice in Veronica was
yelling at me how to hold her and lava
and her new friend
you got that one Tim
[Music]
that's Adam Adam and Katie's Oh her
granddaughter
[Applause]
the one on the left the one on the left
[Music]
okay yeah I think natural fabrics and
it's nice to have I mean there's there's
a bunch of layers you can have okay
as far as sitting a rug in the room is
nice send money dead yeah we're learning
okay oh it's very healthy it's doing
very well Michael and Melissa's baby was
born very very early like 27 weeks if 25
it cannot survive it was born very very
early at 26 you have the lungs begin but
at 25 there's no long stir has to die
the child has to die and just barely
made it and now it's quite healthy okay
it's doing very well I will find a
picture okay okay it's doing very well
the baby's staying there yay okay so I
would if it's me I would put a carpet
first okay because it keeps you from
getting cold in a retreat or when you're
meditating on the floor you have to make
sure
you don't get cold okay because normally
the floor is colder if you're in an
apartment oftentimes the floor even if
the floor is wood or something it's
cement under there cement is very bad
for your body okay it's very very bad to
sit on cement to meditate it's also very
hard and not comfortable but there's
something about cement in my opinion
which hurts your body during meditation
interesting Lee I have tried the marble
and it's very good okay so I'm it can be
hard and it can be good okay if you have
a chance you know
marble is quite good to meditate on I
have a diamond dealer friend I wanted to
do a retreat he said don't worry I have
a bungalow bungalow in English means
like a small retreat cabin he said you
can stay there for two months I said
okay then I went there there were 17
rooms whole staff of cooks and servants
and the whole thing is marble white
marble and it's excellent for meditating
I guess cement is not good okay brick is
okay brick is okay but I will put a
carpet because if you get called it
hurts your meditation a lot if your
bottom gets cold or your legs get cold
it's very bad okay so have some kind of
carpet then personally I like to have
like this one can you hold it up mister
human computer this is great get one of
these okay there's a company in Shenzhen
is called
what's it called FDA no but what's the
the cushion company lions dance cushion
they stole my name but it's okay you can
buy one from them
okay covers your knees okay
converts your knees so you need a carpet
and then you need a big question and
then you need your bottom question and
if you want to try some knee cushions
but that's if you don't have flexible
knees okay all right in my suggestion is
buckwheat and don't use synthetic
materials in the cushion either okay
don't use the foam stuff like that I
think it hurts your meditation
personally okay all right okay second
thing is your eyes eyes can be I've
tried many many many ways I've tried
many years again what I said the other
day is in yoga also if you get in the
habit of looking like you know you're
waiting for my trailer and thirsty right
where you keep your eyes if you keep
your eyes focused in yoga its it's very
helpful for the yoga it hurts less okay
and you're just kind of like that okay
and in the scripture it says keep your
eyes on your nose so many people did
this
and okay it doesn't mean that it's a
very famous stupid thing it means keep
your eyes focused here okay like if you
put your hands here here's your nose
right American longer Chinese shorter
but wherever is your nose put it here
put your hands here and and keep your
eyes focused like that okay it means I'm
my eyes are looking up but I'm not
looking at anything okay don't look at
anything put your eyes in my in my
practice put your eyes slightly up and
don't look at anything okay so you can
do that way and many people ask me do
you have to close your eyes completely
and the scripture says no not at all you
choose okay
what's the rule experiment tried
different ways okay try try what's good
for you what's good for you and what's
good for me is different okay so if it's
me I will focus up I will look at
something like I'm looking at the top of
the door and then I will stop looking at
it and I'll focus here which you know
when you're listening to good music
you're like all right you're thinking
about your boyfriend in high school and
you're not looking at anything right and
that's focus
that's concentration okay so like that
and then I close my eyes but their eyes
are still looking okay and in my opinion
that's one very good for you
the prana moves very well you can also
especially if you didn't sleep well if
you had trouble sleeping if you're
sleepy okay first of all we had a nice
meditation session in I used to have a
retreat center near New York
and we made a funny plan we gave the
students a big lunch and then we had
meditation class and everyone was
struggling yeah and and then we said
okay don't do that now you can see it
doesn't work right so don't don't eat
before you meditate all right
eat something tiny or have some tea or
something but don't and I think coffee
is probably bad for meditation I would
get used to not having coffee during
medicine and then eat lightly or eat
after meditation okay don't don't eat
before meditation unless you need a
little energy it's eat something small
okay now it is legal to have your eyes
like that and just crack them a little
bit open and it keeps you awake when
you're sleepy okay
it helps you stay awake okay so you but
then the chin tends to come down okay
when the eyelids come down the chin
comes down that's not good okay when you
do this it pinches the prana the prana
can't float to to your neck okay so the
neck has to be straight the chin has to
be parallel to the floor okay and but
you can close your eyes halfway and
again don't focus on anything
don't focus I think I found in long
retreat that if you are a person who
likes to crack their eyes make sure
there's nothing in the room that you
like to look at okay for me it's books
when I see books I'm like
so when I do a retreat I always take the
books out of the house the first day I
don't meditate I take the book I take
all the books out of the house and I put
them in boxes and my first in my
three-year retreat for a year and a half
we didn't have any books first for the
first 18 months we didn't have any books
and then you can focus and we didn't
have any Paisley carpets okay when they
call it chalk trouble toe you know
there's a mind only debate don't have
some just have a plain cover okay I like
to sit in front of my altar I like the
altar to be about this high and then I
have a one single color cloth like you
know purple cloth red cloth yellow cloth
and then my eye isn't you know looking
around there's nothing to look at so
okay so keep your chin up and then you
look down and that's okay okay it's
harder to concentrate but if you're
sleepy it's better okay maybe you want
to practice both and see which one's
better for you okay that's tradition I
know Tim I have to speed up okay sit up
straight okay when you meditate sit up
straight it's interesting if you ever
see an x-ray of your spine I think
there's three curves in it it's it's not
straight your spine is not straight okay
nobody's spine is straight you can't sit
up straight there's no such thing the
spine goes like this and but feel
straight okay kinesthetically feel
straight okay and so the spine has to be
straight I think that's one of the big
benefits of a full Lotus you can't it's
hard to have a droopy spine if you're in
a full
you know it's hard to slouch in a folder
I guess you can do it but it's hard okay
if you learn to do it Lotus your spine
will be straight if your spine is
straight a lot of meditation books they
don't talk about the eight Posterous
they just say when does it keep your
spine as straight as a stack of coins
yeah
stack of coins keep your vertebrae like
a stack of coins okay
straight from y'all Dee's happy bucket
she has a system in Taiwan where you put
your coins everything in a box then you
send it to John Bailey or Tim I don't
remember okay so back should be straight
okay shoulders straight okay
I personally I find it helpful my one
yoga teacher I think Theresa was talking
about it they say glue your stump glir
navel to spine the first time I heard it
I'm like what
I like it it's smart it's a good thing
it's a good thing to say push your belly
button towards your spine try to kiss
your spine with your belly button okay
and that would if you tighten the
stomach slightly it tightens the muscles
in the lower back and then you don't get
tired and then you sit up straight so
strong abdomen is the key to a straight
back okay you think you should practice
your back muscles it's not the back
muscles what's keeping the back straight
is is here lower abdomen middle abdomen
okay that's why it's good to do sit-ups
crunches they come crunches notice do
lots of crunches in your yoga you look
cool you have I have a 2-pack I'm
working on I don't like to drink that
much no it's healthier and you can sit
straight okay
so this is the key okay okay all right
so don't complain
during anger or you can complain okay
number four shoulders should be level
it's pretty basic but I do have a friend
who always met it tastes like this I'm
not kidding you know I say your
shoulders are crooked they're like what
it feels normal to them
so that's again why it's useful have a
yoga teacher ballet is very very very
good for keeping your shoulders straight
so in my three-year retreat we did
ballet everyday for a thousand days we
did ballet
we had a what he called a gopher you
know what's a gopher there's a little
like a big mouse they dig a hole there's
the girlfriends around here you don't
see them very often they don't like to
come to the Sun but
we did ballet and we played classical
ballet music and this one gopher come up
and he always listened to the ballet
one day we put offering out next to his
hall and he's like hmm it's a big plate
of cookies and stuff so he he's very
smart he got up on the plate he grabbed
the plate with his two arms and he like
and then the play goes like a dumptruck
Shh it all goes into this hole so watch
your shoulders it's good to have a
teacher it's good to have a younger
teacher I tend to do that I think when
you do a lot of computer work or you're
nervous people give you too much work to
do you so you need a yoga teacher to
bang on your shoulders and tell you okay
so they should be equal all right and
it's useful to push together the two
shoulder blades in the back these two
bones here triangular bones push them
together in the back and then your chest
comes up and then it's it's better for
your spine okay so don't going back
but slightly keep a pressure here you
know here and here
keep keep a little pressure during the
meditation just learn to keep it okay
and it's good for you alright
we did that posted a right what do you
call that punishment this thing where
you hold this in the back that's good
she'll teach you the okay
your head should be the chin should be
level with the ground parallel to the
ground okay and it's very famous
if the chin comes down you'll get sleepy
okay
the prana will be choked and you'll get
sleepy and if the head goes up too high
some people melted ice and then you get
a restless the mind will get restless
okay so to the two most important things
to teach your students about meditation
is it's a middle path between sleepy and
busy okay yeah monkey an elephant okay
too busy and too sleepy and you want to
go between okay if you so if you want to
get sleepy you want the elephant to come
or if you want to invite the monkey okay
so keep your chin level and it helps to
meditate with the other people because
they can tell you you know your chins up
and you're like no it's not that's it we
aren't aware of how our body is you do a
warrior too right I'm like that I'm
always like this you know and people are
like put your arm down I'm like it's
perfect I can feel it you know so you
need someone to look at you and say no
it's not you know okay alright so watch
your head
that's number ABCDE five right number
six how do you keep your mouth okay how
do you keep your mouth it's important if
the mouth is too tight it will make you
tired and the meditation won't go well
okay if it's like this here you have a
very important three channels there are
72 thousand channels in the body three
are most important they they are here
they start here okay one is here and one
is here and one is here and they go
under the skin under the skull you come
down and they go in front of your spine
about a quarter-inch how many two
millimeters two millimeters five
millimeters half centimeter and they
start here the three channels start here
okay there's two here which is why you
have nostrils the they form around those
channels in the womb okay so and here
there's a knot and these three channels
cross and they continue okay so if you
go like that you are choking your prana
and you won't have a good meditation and
if you smile it loosens up these two
channels and that listens this knot and
then the prana flows sweet so a small
Mona Lisa smile you can you find the
Mona Lisa I went to the Louvre with
Veronica and her sister you know she's
about half a mile away but if you look
carefully they think maybe Leonardo da
Vinci's pants fell down or some and
she's I don't know I'm not it's true
but she's like maybe some days open I
don't know she say that smile you should
have in meditation there you go
right something's going on well maybe I
just got too much in the gardener yeah
anyways small smile like that I call
Mona Lisa smile very famous okay not a
big smile her channels are doing very
well the book says keep your mouth in a
natural position okay some people
meditate and their mouth starts to drop
open open up you know and in a long
meditation it will get dry the mouth
will get dry and then you'll be
swallowing all the time okay if you
meditate a lot swallowing smells sounds
like a garbage truck no if you meditate
a lot if you meditate a lot swallowing
is very disturbing it sounds like in
trying to meditate in New York when the
garbage trucks outside okay so so close
your mouth and keep it moist keep it
moist okay if you keep your mouth open
if you breathe through your mouth your
mouth will get dry and then you swallow
and then the garbage truck comes okay
and you will get this term okay there's
a custom in some capacity niche and I
will talk more about it later
but you don't open your eyes you don't
look at things you don't play music you
don't look at mandalas you know you
don't drink during meditation you don't
disturb your meditation okay that's a
tradition in this lineage and I think
it's correct okay
so drink drink throughout the day drink
pretty well before men
and then take a nice pee-pee they didn't
say that right take a big peepee just
before meditations okay all right mmm so
the mouth should be comfortable natural
and not open and a small smile
okay loose loose mom okay number seven
okay here we go that's just about how to
keep your tongue and I don't know they
say keep the tongue against your palate
and I tried like twenty five different
ways my llama fine isn't just natural
just whatever is normal you know don't
think about it there's a long story in
the scripture about how you won't get
thirsty if it's in the right place you
can that's something you have to
experiment I just tell you experiment
okay learn to experiment okay don't get
stuck with one cushion or one way of
sitting okay try everything same with
yoga you know go to a hundred teachers
and see which one is good for your body
because what's good for your body is not
good for my body okay number this is
optional okay I mean it's sometimes it's
included in the aim and sometimes it's
not included and you get seven okay so
sometimes they count this one and
sometimes they don't count this one cuz
it's not technically your posture it's
how you breathe okay it's how you
breathe if you can breathe through your
nose breathe through your nose okay if
you have a cold or you have boogers or
you have allergies you're not a bad
person you can't breathe through your
mouth
or your ears
okay okay the some days you just you
know it stuffed up you know you can't do
anything okay so some days it's gonna be
stuffed up then breathe through your
mouth but traditionally breathe through
your nose you have a lot of what they
call these things sinus cavities here
and there's a big school of yoga that
says it's very important to breathe up
into the sinus cavities if you can so
you can try it if you have time
Monday Tuesday try to breathe up into
the cavities and I think it actually
helps your oxygen get to your brain or
something it's a big thing every morning
in my retreat for a thousand days I did
this there's a soft tube you can push up
and then you do neti you do a you pour
water in your sinuses so if you have
training about that if someone teaches
you how to do it it can help your
meditation I did it for every day during
my sphere retreat you just start with
this little pot and you you go like this
and it takes us a few days to learn how
and then it will go up and pour out the
other nostril and then you do it this
way and it pours out if you don't do it
right you choke and you spit up but you
have to be patient and then if you want
to there's a medical tube catheter that
they use for pb's and you can push it
you push it up your nose and you clean
it up and it goes all the way back to
your you can feel it in the back of your
throat okay so I used to do that
it's pretty cool it can help your
meditation especially in your laundry
tree okay the goal is to get more oxygen
to your brain okay so check it out
experiment with it okay don't say it's
stupid it might be stupid but try it try
everything okay I found that for the
first time in my life my my passages
were really open and I could breathe a
lot easier and that made the meditation
go better because I got more oxygen okay
but you need training someone you have
to learn from someone who knows how to
do you can tear the tissue here so you
need some training somebody has to teach
you how to do it okay people use a
thread in ancient times with knocks on
it and they go and then the thread goes
back and then they know that's that I I
did it every day with a tube with a
catheter plastic tube it's cool but it's
for long between okay if you do a long
routine you can try but you learn from
someone who has a good teacher okay
because you can hurt your these are very
sensitive tissues okay so don't do it
from a book don't do it from in YouTube
YouTube
okay okay good
and as I told you personally and I've
been many ten in many years that thing
about a full exhale is very very helpful
okay
anytime you do a three or four week
retreat if you're a normal person you
will get long low means tightness in the
chest nervous feeling headaches crazy
thoughts upset thoughts anger shaking
your hands okay if you meditate more
than two weeks your you will get it okay
and you have to know about it and
personally I found that if I exhale
normally and then push a little more out
I don't get it
I don't get that okay so it's important
if you feel yourself start getting
nervous or you you feel I don't know
very sensitive you know very very
sensitive you get upset easily okay then
try to breathe out longer okay more
breath out when you reach the end of the
breath a natural pause then a little bit
more okay just push out a little bit
more okay and also when you do forward
bends and stuff like that some teachers
really advise it what's his name Rodney
is big on that and it's nice okay if you
have some obstacle when you do forward
bend then you can try that okay when you
get down there and then breathe out
again and you can go further okay
the stomach will come in that's one of
the most important meditation advices I
can give you okay if you meditate
regularly
and you let prana build up in your chest
you're gonna have a bad time
you're gonna have that mind will get
irritated and the body will get nervous
and okay if you see it happening work
harder on your exhales okay if it gets
serious eat heavy greasy food that's
traditional method to stop it okay so
eat popcorn is very popular at Diamond
Mountain with more butter than popcorn
okay
and it it Chuck we call long Chuck no
Chuck means it's it breaks the tightness
in your chest okay my mom I used to give
me a whole bowl of butter bottom our COO
say butter Marc ooh he said I got Louise
it's all bottom I'll make your butt no
no I'm okay
it's a whole bowl of butter ghee ghee
clarified butter and it has some cubes
of boiled flour oil dough and then you
put lots of sugar cuz you can't eat it
but definitely it breaks through that
alone yeah it does other things too okay
but I've done it and how it helps okay
so greasy heavy food if you start to get
nervous in your meditation okay all
right if you especially if you're in
retreat we're gonna take a pee-pee break
soon I promise
I gotta finish this or Tim's gonna kill
me and then you won't have any teacher
we'll see what book does jetsam kapa
used for these eight he uses gum rim
Bhavana crema baba nakooma written by
combination okay who wrote the famous
diamond cutter commentary okay greatest
pecan and I taught it you it's probably
there's some recordings if you're
interested in those three he wrote three
short meditation manuals so there's
three Bhavana chromis and they became
the standard for all Tibetan schools
Sakia car GU galoop NEMA they all use
comma Sheila's bum in a coma okay so
it's a great book and it has all this
stuff is in it okay
[Music]
yeah sometimes these are called the
eight-point posture of vital China vital
China is a tantric Buddha it's the
center of the five gianni Buddhist
meditation Buddhist color is white okay
and has a special ability to relate to
people okay when viral China goes to a
bar he acts like a truck driver went
viral chen ik goes to teaching he looks
like a mark went viral channel goes to
DCI he has a tie expensive suit okay so
this is one of China's special quality
van chana can talk to anybody in their
own language okay that's better to me
okay
so some often times these eight or seven
qualities are connected to each other
and when you teach them they say I'm
gonna teach you the biogenic in okay by
Rocinha okay by Rocinha if I means many
different kinds the word very comes from
by Roche means light like shining light
okay and R and L are interchangeable in
Sanskrit solokha which means the
illuminated world the world loca and
Roche are the same root loci came into
lucid words like that okay so by Rocinha
means can can appear in any costume
according to what people need okay
that's the viral channel okay all right
so not all roaches are crawling around
on the ground that's it
we finished eight-point posture okay
so we're gonna take a break now and
stretch your legs have something to
drink okay and then we'll come back and
we'll keep going